Guide to the World War II ration coupon collection, 1942-1946 RL.01419
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
World War II ration coupon collection
1942-1946
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United States. Office of Price Administration
RL.01419
0.2 Linear Feet
Collection consists of ration coupons, stickers, permits, and certificates for tires, bicycles, typewriters, sugar, shoes, fuel oil, gasoline, and food which were issued by the Office of Price Administration between 1942-1946. There are duplicates for a few items.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Transfer, 2008.
Historical Note
The Office of Price Administration and Civilian Supply was created by Exec. order no. 8734, April 11, 1941; in the new agency were combined the price and consumer divisions of the National Defense Advisory Commission; name of agency changed to Office of Price Administration by Exec. order no. 8874, Aug. 28, 1941.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of ration coupons, stickers, permits, and certificates for tires, bicycles, typewriters, sugar, shoes, fuel oil, gasoline, and food which were issued by the Office of Price Administration between 1942-1946. There are duplicates for a few items.
Arrangement note
Organized by product type, then by number of items.
Rationing -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Energy conservation -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Food supply -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Social aspects -- United States; United States. Office of Price Administration
- Tire certificate A and B, 33.9598 cm x 8.5725 cm (13.37" x 3.375") (Box 1)
- Tire dealers part of tire certificate, 64.135 cm x 8.255 cm (25.25" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Nontransferable certificate for the purchase of tires or tubes or recapping service, 21.2598 cm x 55.88 cm (8.37" x 22.0") (Box 1)
- Certificate for acquisition of new passenger automobile purchased on or before January 1, 1942, 20.32 cm x 61.9125 cm (8.0" x 24.375") (Box 1)
- Certificate to purchase 1942 model passenger car for use, 41.91 cm x 21.59 cm (16.5" x 8.5") (Box 1)
- Stove purchase certificate, 17.145 cm x 8.255 cm (6.75" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Stove purchase certificate 1943, 20.32 cm x 8.89 cm (8.0" x 3.5") (Box 1)
- Typewriter rental certificate, 17.78 cm x 19.05 cm (7.0" x 7.5") (Box 1)
- Application for certificate to rent class B typewriters, 20.32 cm x 26.67 cm (8.0" x 10.5") (Box 1)
- Certificate authorizing acquisition of new adult bicycles, 64.77 cm x 27.94 cm (25.5" x 11.0") (Box 1)
- Rubber footwear purchase certificate (1943), 20.32 cm x 8.89 cm (8.0" x 3.5") (Box 1)
- Rubber footwear purchase certificate (1944), 17.145 cm x 8.255 cm (6.75" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Certificate of registration to buy, sell, and transfer men's rubber boots and rubber work shoes, 1942; 20.32 cm x 10.16 cm (8.0" x 4.0") (Box 1)
- Shoe purchase certificate, 1943-1944; 20.32 cm x 8.89 cm (8.0" x 3.5") (Box 1)
- Non-rationed shoes, 1943; 20.32 cm x 13.97 cm (8.0" x 5.5") (Box 1)
- Special shoe stamps, 1943; 26.035 cm x 13.0175 cm (10.25" x 5.125") (Box 1)
- Non-rationed shoe stamps, 1943; 27.94 cm x 14.2875 cm (11.0" x 5.625") (Box 1)
- Certificate to acquire men's rubber boots and rubber work shoes, 1942; 20.955 cm x 55.88 cm (8.25" x 22.0") (Box 1)
- Sugar purchase certificate, 1942-1945; 19.685 cm x 9.525 cm (7.75" x 3.75") (Box 1)
- Sugar allowance coupon for home food processing 1 pound, 1942-1945; 21.59 cm x 21.59 cm (8.5" x 8.5") (Box 1)
- Sugar allowance coupon for home food processing 3 pounds, 1942-1945; 21.59 cm x 21.59 cm (8.5" x 8.5") (Box 1)
- Food ration certificate, 1942; 60.325 cm x 8.382 cm (23.75" x 3.3") (Box 1)
- Processed foods - ration card for residents of border zone in Mexico, 16.51 cm x 20.32 cm (6.5" x 8.0") (Box 1)
- Meats - fat - fish - cheeses ration card for residents of border zone in Mexico, 16.8148 cm x 22.86 cm (6.62" x 9.0") (Box 1)
- War ration book one, 26.67 cm x 20.32 cm (10.5" x 8.0") (Box 1)
- War ration book two, 1942; 28.8798 cm x 10.795 cm (11.37" x 4.25") (Box 1)
- War ration book three, 1943; 29.21 cm x 10.795 cm (11.5" x 4.25") (Box 1)
- War ration book five, 1945; 14.605 cm x 5.3975 cm (5.75" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 4 consumer coupons (Zone A-1), 51.1048 cm x 16.1925 cm (20.12" x 6.375") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 4 consumer coupons (Zone B-1), 50.8 cm x 16.51 cm (20.0" x 6.5") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 4A consumer coupons (Zone B-2), 1944; 51.1048 cm x 16.51 cm (20.12" x 6.5") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 4B consumer coupons (Zone A-2), 1945-1946; 51.1048 cm x 16.1925 cm (20.12" x 6.375") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 5 consumer coupons (Zone A-1), 1942-1945; 35.56 cm x 16.51 cm (14.0" x 6.5") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 5 consumer coupons (Zone B-1), 1942-1945; 35.56 cm x 16.51 cm (14.0" x 6.5") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 5B consumer coupons (Zone A-2), 1942-1945; 40.005 cm x 16.51 cm (15.75" x 6.5") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 5A consumer coupons (Zone B-2), 1944; 39.37 cm x 16.1925 cm (15.5" x 6.375") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 5B consumer coupons (Zone B-2), 1945-1946; 40.005 cm x 16.1925 cm (15.75" x 6.375") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil ration class 6 consumer coupons (Zone A-1), 1945-1946; 35.56 cm x 16.1925 cm (14.0" x 6.375") (Box 1)
- V - Fuel oil ration class 1 consumer coupons (red), 1942; 44.45 cm x 27.305 cm (17.5" x 10.75") (Box 1)
- V - Fuel oil ration class 1 consumer coupons (purple), 1942; 44.45 cm x 27.305 cm (17.5" x 10.75") (Box 1)
- V - Fuel oil ration class 1 consumer coupon (green), 1942; 44.45 cm x 27.305 cm (17.5" x 10.75") (Box 1)
- V - Fuel oil ration class 2 consumer coupons (green), 1942; 44.45 cm x 27.305 cm (17.5" x 10.75") (Box 1)
- V - Fuel oil ration class 3 consumer coupons (1 gallon), 1942; 32.385 cm x 26.67 cm (12.75" x 10.5") (Box 1)
- V - Fuel oil ration class 3 consumer coupons (5 gallon), 1942; 32.385 cm x 26.67 cm (12.75" x 10.5") (Box 1)
- V - Fuel oil ration class 3 consumer coupons (25 gallon), 1942; 32.385 cm x 26.67 cm (12.75" x 10.5") (Box 1)
- V - Fuel oil ration class 3 consumer coupons (100 gallon), 1942; 32.385 cm x 26.67 cm (12.75" x 10.5") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil - one gallon inventory coupons, 1942; 32.385 cm x 26.67 cm (12.75" x 10.5") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil - 100 gallon inventory coupons, 1942; 32.385 cm x 26.67 cm (12.75" x 10.5") (Box 1)
- Permits delivery of one A unit, 1942; 10.4648 cm x 5.3975 cm (4.12" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- Bulk coupon permits delivery of 100 gallons, 1942; 12.7 cm x 5.3975 cm (5.0" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil exchange certificate, 1942; 20.32 cm x 25.4 cm (8.0" x 10.0") (Box 1)
- Fuel oil deposit certificate, 1941-1945; 20.32 cm x 7.62 cm (8.0" x 3.0") (Box 1)
- Application and registration certificate for fuel oil dealer or supplier, 26.3398 cm x 40.64 cm (10.37" x 16.0") (Box 1)
- One gallon inventory gasoline coupons, 1942; 12.3698 cm x 5.08 cm (4.87" x 2.0") (Box 1)
- C supplemental gasoline ration, 10.16 cm x 5.3975 cm (4.0" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- E non-highway gasoline ration, 1942; 10.16 cm x 5.3975 cm (4.0" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- R non-highway gasoline ration, 1942-1943; 10.16 cm x 5.3975 cm (4.0" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- R non-highway ration, 1943; 10.16 cm x 5.3975 cm (4.0" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- T-2 transportation mileage ration, 1942-1943; 10.16 cm x 5.3975 cm (4.0" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- T-1 transport mileage ration (D), 1943; 10.16 cm x 5.3975 cm (4.0" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- T-1 transport mileage ration (V6), 1942; 10.16 cm x 5.3975 cm (4.0" x 2.125") (Box 1)
- Windshield sticker (A), 1942-1945; 6.35 cm x 8.255 cm (2.5" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Windshield sticker (B), 1942-1945; 6.35 cm x 8.255 cm (2.5" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Mileage ration T, 6.35 cm x 8.255 cm (2.5" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Gasoline ration card A, 1942; 10.16 cm x 8.255 cm (4.0" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Gasoline ration card B-1, 1942; 10.16 cm x 8.255 cm (4.0" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Gasoline ration card B-2, 1942; 11.0998 cm x 7.9375 cm (4.37" x 3.125") (Box 1)
- Gasoline ration card B-3, 1942; 10.16 cm x 8.255 cm (4.0" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Gasoline ration card X, 1942; 10.16 cm x 8.255 cm (4.0" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Acknowledgment and authorization of delivery gasoline and fuel oil, 20.32 cm x 8.89 cm (8.0" x 3.5") (Box 1)
- Mileage rationing program certificate, 64.135 cm x 8.255 cm (25.25" x 3.25") (Box 1)
- Gasoline purchase permit, 1942-1945; 17.145 cm x 8.5725 cm (6.75" x 3.375") (Box 1)
- Gasoline deposit certificate, 1943-1945; 20.32 cm x 7.62 cm (8.0" x 3.0") (Box 1)
- A - basic mileage ration, 19.05 cm x 19.05 cm (7.5" x 7.5") (Box 1)
- A - basic mileage ration, 12.7 cm x 20.32 cm (5.0" x 8.0") (Box 1)
- B - supplemental mileage ration, 1942; 9.1948 cm x 16.1925 cm (3.62" x 6.375") (Box 1)
- C - supplemental gasoline ration, 18.415 cm x 27.305 cm (7.25" x 10.75") (Box 1)
- C2 - supplemental gasoline ration, 18.415 cm x 27.305 cm (7.25" x 10.75") (Box 1)
- D motorcycle ration, 1943; 18.415 cm x 22.225 cm (7.25" x 8.75") (Box 1)
- E non-highway gasoline ration, 1943; 21.2598 cm x 21.59 cm (8.37" x 8.5") (Box 1)
- Gasoline one gallon inventory coupons, 1943-1945; 32.385 cm x 27.305 cm (12.75" x 10.75") (Box 1)
- Gasoline one gallon bulk coupons, 1942-1945; 32.385 cm x 26.67 cm (12.75" x 10.5") (Box 1)